this is station Nord in Greenland
it's a Danish base
as the territory is part of the Kingdom of Denmark
and therefore the European country
is responsible for its defense
station Nord ranks as the northernmost Danish base and the
second northernmost continuously inhabited place on earth
therefore  the job of the six soldiers stationed there
is largely just to keep it inhabitable  militarily
it doesn't have tremendous purpose beyond existing
the Danes say to search their sovereignty in
the vast emptiness of northern Greenland
perhaps the six thousand foot gravel
runway is of some strategic value
but really it's a research camp that
happens to be run by the Danish military
all summer long
it sees a nonstop Rota of scientists
it's a similar story down in messersvig
this is an old base that at this point is pretty much just
maintained and is occasionally used for scientific purposes
perhaps the best known of Denmark's
arctic installations is den博格
that's because it's the base of the country's
primary military capabilities in the region
dog sled patrols
this function originated in World War II when Nazi
forces were hiding weather stations in eastern
Greenland in order to improve the accuracy of their
forecasts in support of their military pursuits
and still to this day
the dog sleds are the Danish military's primary means of
patrolling almost ten thousand miles of coastline
teams of two set out for multi month missions
hopping between resupply huts refilled by boat and
aircraft during the summer months and taking years
to complete one full patrol of the coast
but dogsled patrol of course does
little beyond assert sovereignty
aside from that
there's technically a small Danish
installation at Kangerlussuaq airport
as it's home to the one and only Danish military
aircraft permanently stationed in Greenland
a bombardier cl 604 challenger surveillance aircraft
but that's pretty much the entirety of Danish
military presence north of the arctic circle
a couple of bases staffed by a couple
dozen personnel and some dogs
this military geography or lack thereof forms
part of the basis for the most recent proposal for
the us to just outright purchase Greenland
Denmark is a nato member
and therefore some military leaders in the us are
concerned about such a lack of defense capability
in such a large region so close to the us  of course
the proposal appears preposterous
at first
large land purchases by one country from another have not
meaningfully happened since the era of colonialism
and the very appeal of the idea is rooted in the same
manner of exploitation of a territory's resources
be them human or natural
Greenland however is in a unique situation
it's not quite like Canada or Mexico or the Panama
Canal or the Gaza strip or any of the other slices of
earth American president Trump has proposed Annexing
Greenland acts as an autonomous self
governing territory of the Kingdom of Denmark
it's similar to the relationship
between Scotland and the uk
for example  culturally
politically and geographically
it's almost entirely isolated from Denmark
but less so economically
Denmark pays for about two thirds of
Greenland's government budget
and its contributions add up to about
a quarter of the territory's GDP  meanwhile
Greenland pays no taxes to Denmark
it's a one way flow of money
therefore  looking at it at the simplest possible level
excluding politics  culture  history
any of the practical concerns
or the way people actually feel in reality right now
it's easy to grasp a scenario
where all parties come out happy
the us gets the territory it wants
Greenland gets a greater cash inflow in exchange
and Denmark stops having to send hundreds of
millions of dollars a year to a far off territory
but considering the core of the purported value is
wrapped up in the strategic benefit for the military
examining the need requires an understanding of the
military geography across the entire far north
and here  nestled on the coast of north star bay
is the simplest explanation for how Denmark can have
such a minor presence in its massive territory
this is the United States largest
arctic installation ptutik spacebase
compare to the Danish equivalent
this is colossal
it's got a ten thousand foot three thousand meter runway
it's staffed by about six hundred personnel
it's got the world's northernmost deepwater port
it's really a fully equipped us military
base like those that dot the entire world
just really really far north
its location makes it a three to four hour flight to all of
Russia's northern coast or just over five hours to Moscow
given this proximity
the base's population peaked at more than
ten thousand during the height of tensions
with the soviet union in the sixties
today  its role centers around missile tracking
signals intelligence and satellite communications
although it regularly hosts fighter jets and other
offensive aircraft to train for their operations in the
environment should the need arise in a conflict
petticoff however is an anomaly
it is by far the largest military facility west of
the prime Meridian and north of the arctic circle
its next nearest neighboring facility is Canadian
forces station alert an hour's flight to the north
not much detail is publicly known about
what specifically the station does
but broadly it's a joint Canadian
American signals intelligence facility
taking advantage of the location for
surveillance and monitoring of whatever Nato
the us or Canada deems a threat  physically
it's closer to Moscow than it is to Ottawa
which historically allowed for greater
surveillance capabilities on the soviet union
and today allows the same with Russia
it's so far north in fact that the curvature of the earth
prevents it from having a line of sight with communication
satellites in geosynchronous orbit around the equator
therefore  the Canadians built a network of microwave
repeaters on mountain tops across Ellesmere island
that each have line of sight with each other
allowing transmissions to reach satellites via Eureka
a small combo research military base that is
just far enough south to see the satellites
1 there's also a Canadian military presence down on Baffin
island at the naval facility which is on the cusp of opening
following more than a decade of construction delays
its purpose is pretty simple
it's home to two big storage tanks to
refuel Canadian naval vessels
allowing them to patrol longer and further into the arctic
which is something the military is keen to
do as sea ice shrinks and the waterways
become navigable for more weeks each year
beyond that  there's a training facility in resolute bay
and as far as major permanent Canadian
military facilities in the arctic go
that's about it
to the west
one might expect that the most militarized country on earth
would also have the most militarized arctic territory
but that's far from the case
in fact
the only Permanent American facilities north of the
Arctic circle in Alaska are long range radar sites
used by norad for early detection of missiles
aircraft and other potential threats
although these days they are primarily run
by civilian contractors who fly in and out of
the attached airfields to do work
most are not staffed full time
particularly by enlisted service members
just south of the arctic circle though
is a far more significant presence
clustered primarily around fairbanks is a series of
bases with the full gamut of us military capabilities
there's the largest concentration of fifth
generation fighter jets in the world
the core of the us's anti ballistic missile defense system
twenty thousand active duty troops
it's a massive cluster of might
but it's historically been optimized less for projecting
power to the north but more so to protect from Eastbound
threats from Russia  North Korea  China and other Asian
Nations  considering it's on the great circle
path between the two continents
Russia's arctic posture however is quite different
tracking westward
it starts modest
the country's easternmost facility of any
significance is referred to as polar star
coincidentally
it was built in a town that was originally
established to assert Russian sovereignty on the islands
as the Americans and Canadians
attempted to claim it a century ago
that town sat empty after the last resident was
killed by a polar bear in two thousand three
but in its place the Russian
military built this small base
it's only accessible by helicopter and boats
and little is known about what happens there
beyond the operations of this radar facility and
the associated anti aircraft missile systems
but without an airfield
it has little offensive capability
that's why a two hour flight to the
west they're building this
temp airbase
this outpost has existed since the fifties
and like most of the country's
military facilities in the arctic
it closed following the collapse of the soviet union
but then over the past decade
it's not only reopened
but has been built up into a hugely capable facility
the latest high quality satellite
imagery doesn't even show it
but what was a gravel airstrip has since been
upgraded into a sixty nine hundred foot twenty
one hundred meter paved runway capable of
accommodating most military aircraft year round
the corresponding base is massive compared
to most equivalents at this latitude
housing around two hundred and fifty personnel
and that's not even the country's most capable arctic base
to the west there's russia's northernmost negrskoye
base which also since this imagery was taken paved this
runway and expanded it to eleven thousand five hundred
feet or thirty five hundred meters allowing it to host
truly any aircraft including fighter jets
in fact  in twenty twenty one
Russia flew two fighter jets from the base
to the north pole as a show of force
the growing capability of this base
paired with its geography
has rattled the west
Nagurskoye is less than a three hour
flight to Ptichye space base
and it's also the closest Russian Airbase to Washington dc
negroskoy is backed up by rugechev airbase
a ninety minute flight to the south
and then there are a few more minor facilities
scattered along the country's northern coast
there's also a huge concentration of military might on
the Kola Peninsula bordering Norway and Finland
although Nato also has a
significant build up in this region
it's in part a byproduct of the fact that this is the
most hospitable and populated region of the arctic
thanks to the comparatively warm air
brought in by the Gulf stream
but throughout the rest of the arctic
the distribution of facilities
tells a pretty succinct story
Russia has been far more concerned than pretty much any
country in building up its military presence in the far
north
of course
dosa on maps aren't what truly matters militarily
they're a proxy for capability
and capability is what matters in conflict
but there too
Russia appears to have the upper hand
beyond its bases
the primary manner in which the us is able to bring
military capability to anywhere is through its naval
resources  it has one of the largest and almost
certainly most powerful navies in the world
and between cruisers  destroyers
aircraft carriers  and more
it's capable of bringing a huge
amount of force truly anywhere
except the arctic
submarines can operate in the arctic year
round since they float beneath the ice
but beyond that
no other us ships have hardened hulls
capable of cutting through sea ice
that means that for the majority of the year
the arctic is the one area of the world to
which the us can't project power by sea
of course the solution to this is icebreakers
they not only can access frozen areas themselves
but they can cut a channel for other
ships that lack hardened hulls
the us has three of these
all operated by the u s coast guard
Russia meanwhile has forty one of them
this includes a series of brand new nuclear
powered icebreakers that are more powerful and
longer ranged than any other in the world
and this imbalance exists across just about
every military capability in the arctic
whatever the us has
Russia has more of
they have more training
more equipment designed for the extreme cold
more snow capable vehicles  more ports
more airfields
their GPS alternative navigation system  glonass
even has more satellites reaching higher latitudes
giving it better coverage in the polar regions
and all of these capabilities
especially in the period leading up
to Russia's invasion of Ukraine
have been growing faster than at
any time since the cold war
it's become a cliche over the last decade to call the
renewed interest in the far north as a race for the arctic
but ever since two thousand seven
when an emboldened Russia planted its
flag underwater on the north pole
it's been hard to think of it as anything less
and it's been hard to think of any nation aside
from Russia as the current leader in that race
in just about all metrics russia's leading the way
but while russia's actions have encouraged a response
by the rest of the world to hurriedly catch up
Russia for its part has viewed its northern activity
as less an exceptional push into an underdeveloped
corner of the map and more a natural progression as
part of a larger cohesive defense strategy
this all centers around the Kola Peninsula
in the past decade
Russia has heavily reinvested in this region by
modernizing the severomorsk air bases and upgrading
the okolnyaya and gadjevsk submarine bases
critically though
this is reinvestment
historically
the facilities along this peninsula
were central to soviet defense
and as Russia's relations with the west have gotten colder
while its ambitions have grown larger
they're viewing the region's defense
capabilities as vitally important once again
as analysts have noted
this investment has little to do with any sort
of race to the arctic or the arctic itself
and more to do with a return to a
strategy called bastion defense
effectively
the country wants to create an air and sea buffer between
itself and other nations that ensures freedom of movement
across the barents and Norwegian seas for its northern fleet
along with its increasingly important
northern natural gas industry
what makes this particular bastion so critical for Russian
defense is the fact that this area harbors what's
believed to be about two thirds of Russia's nuclear strike
capabilities in its ballistic missile submarines which
operates as a key nuclear deterrent and the nation's
second strike capabilities should it be attacked
so while at the periphery of the
world from most's perspective
this area is already central to Russian defense
which means increased traffic creates
an increasingly paranoid Russia
the invasion of Ukraine has only added to the Paranoia
for one
Russia's invasion has shaken up the map of the high north
pushing the long neutral neighbors in
Finland and Sweden to join Nato
making the high north a seven one split
between Nato and non Nato Nations
while a repercussion of their own actions this
has only served to further the sense of
encirclement for Russian military planners
and making Russia more concerned is the fact that it
was the northern fleet's ground resources that led
the invasion into Ukraine in the first place
in late January and early February of twenty twenty two
when Russian onlookers began to share on social media
trainload after trainload moving tanks and army trucks south
it was resources being mobilized from
the arctic that they were capturing
in the weeks that followed those resources much of the 200th
brigade were dramatically beaten back then bogged down on
the outskirts of karkiv ensuring there'd be no quick return
while exact numbers are difficult to come by
only an estimated fifth of the two hundredth Brigade
has remained stationed on the Kola Peninsula
while the failed attempt to seize Kiev
decimated the fleet's ground forces
at the same time that Russia has moved
troops away from the high north
the high north has also become more
economically central to the country
total trade across the north sea route hit
an all time high in twenty twenty two
while new LNG terminals above the arctic circle went
online using the north sea route to move product to China
and with the subsequent sanctions that came with invasion
Russia has diverted traffic of crude oil
bound for Asia through the arctic
while reportedly beginning to build a ghost fleet
of tankers that have been quietly tracking across
the region to avoid sanctions entirely
taken together
what's long been understood from a Russian
perspective as a military stronghold has
become increasingly important economically
increasingly hostile militarily
and increasingly vulnerable
feeling cornered
the nation has taken to lashing out
with aggressive military maneuvers
joint military exercises with China
and going as far as destroying
infrastructure like undersea cables
much of the sensationalism of the increasing military
importance of the arctic then can be explained by the
collision of two very different geopolitical narratives
in the west the us and its allies in Nato are dramatically
falling behind Russia in arctic capabilities
so it must rush to catch up  in Russia
it seems the rest of the world is pushing to
encircle and endanger its northern coast
an area strategically important
for its defense and its economy
so it must dig in
but both these competing narratives run into a Stark
reality of which Greenland sits directly in the middle
there's just not a lot of actual infrastructure  military
civilian or otherwise in the upper reaches of the arctic
all real American and Russian might hovers
around the very edge of the arctic circle
while the island and its military personnel
numbered in the hundreds from a strategic
perspective represents largely a blank space on the map
China for one has come knocking
with a reversal of a rare earth elements mining ban
in twenty thirteen by Greenland's parliament
the island's rich natural resources
caught the eye of investors
Chinese firms seeking to back
uranium mining in the island's south
zinc mining in the island's north
and oilfield production off its coast had all begun
doing their due diligence on how to open up shop
in twenty twenty five
the tenbrise mine in southern Greenland
optimistically projected to produce over half of
the global non Chinese rare earth elements
went up for sale and garnered heavy Chinese interest
only heavy American and Danish lobbying in early
twenty twenty five pushed the sale to an American
firm for reportedly a fraction of market value
in each case of Chinese mining interest
the fear of the nation's increased influence in
the region has pushed the projects back
but these increasingly accessible rare earth elements
are bound to keep international firms coming back
it stands to reason given the demand and the potential
economic windfall for the island that it's only a matter of
time before a foreign mining company gets a real foothold
and still  the commercial appeal is dwarfed by
the strategic and defense appeal
there's just really no landmass as centrally
located to the high arctic as Greenland
and no place that so cleanly splits
the divide between east and west
nor sits so near to critical sea ways that
serve as entrance and exit to the high north
seemingly so far beyond the purview of Denmark's
focus for the emboldened it feels up for grabs
given Denmark's self admitted lack of
defense investments in the island
the us's increasingly bad faith
dealing with the rest of the world
and the vampiric narrative tension in the arctic
the future of Greenland can be
presented as a rhetorical this or that
if not America  then who
but Greenland is not empty
its people do have a say
nato is not just an empty vessel for the us to control
and Denmark
though behind
is not asleep at the wheel
in response to president Trump's rhetoric
Greenland's prime minister has held talks with European
leaders about maintaining its SEMI autonomous standing
Nato countries have talked about
deploying troops to Greenland
and Denmark's announced two billion dollars in
increased defense spending for the island
the capability gap in the arctic is real
it's clear that for a us military so
accustomed to unequivocal superiority
the imbalance in infrastructure and
experience is uncomfortable
what's less clear is how sovereign
control of Greenland would help that
the us already has a major
military presence in the territory
and there's never been a major impediment
to operations or expansions at bitufi
spacebase due to the lack of sovereignty
in fact  over recent years
the us has announced plans to
upgrade and expand the facility
and while Danish and greenlandic
authorities didn't immediately agree
a short negotiation with a few
concessions led to rather swift approval
outside of Greenland
other Nato members like Canada also recognize
the gaps in the alliance's arctic footprint
so they are already spending huge sums to
upgrade their facilities and capabilities
surely they would be happy for the us to spend
those huge sums in their territory instead
to military leaders
the status quo is untenable
but considering how miniscule the u
s's arctic capabilities are
there's enormous ability to expand before it
becomes necessary to just buy Greenland
rather than do a normal ad read here
i just want to play the trailer to the newest
show produced by windover productions
it's called abolish everything
do you ever feel like we'd all be better off if
everyone liked stuff less and yelled at each other more
you're holding the door open on the train
deep underground in New York city a radical movement
is taking shape and i'd like you to join us
each night gathered in our meeting house four
brave abolitionists will tell us why we should
eliminate some aspect of society forever
abolish the dentist
speakerphone  bomb  spears  stretching
yeah here we bring it on
and their testimony will be heard and
rebutted by the political establishment
a panel of improvisers hell bent
on preserving the status quo
the boys want to see ya
don't want to hear ya
so why do you hate what god gave to you
have you ever taken a lot of adderall for your body
the only way to stop a bad guy with a
speakerphone is a good guy with a speakerphone
at the end of the show the people
will decide what gets abolished
who gets this cartoonish stack of
coins with a dollar sign on it
and who receives an invitation to our
world championship season finale  stand up  improv
powerpoint presentations
if our movement is successful
all of these things will eventually be banned
this is abolish everything
the first episode of abolish everything is already out
and more are coming out every two
weeks exclusively on nebula
and a lot of people seem to be really enjoying it
it's obviously pretty different from
what we've made in the past
but i think it's the kind of comedy that
will appeal especially to wendover fans
as comedians make rather ridiculous powerpoint
presentations loosely grounded in reality to pitch
their case to the political establishment
if you want to watch this or any of Nebula's great
unique nebula originals use the link nebula tv windover
to get forty percent off an annual subscription